Justin Florentine: Good morning, Frame Transactors!
marc | wolovim: Hello, everyone. We are gonna get kicked off here. Welcome to Frame Transaction Breakout Number 5. Today is September 22nd, 2026.
marc | wolovim: I will post the agenda in the chat here.
marc | wolovim: And today's agenda includes the usual bits. I don't think we have much to say about spec changes or test releases, which means we'll get quickly into
marc | wolovim: DevNet updates, and then, any client updates, and then the rest of the time will be available for any new or existing proposals, and we've solicited some community feedback from
marc | wolovim: Wallet, tooling devs, app devs. So, any of that is very much welcome.
marc | wolovim: After we get through the first few items here.
marc | wolovim: So…
marc | wolovim: Unless I'm mistaken, no changes to the spec. I posted a forecast link in here which shows you all of the PRs against 8141. There's 13 open right now.
marc | wolovim: My understanding is that…
marc | wolovim: Each of these are secondary concerns to the primary concern being getting Frame's DevNet Zero up and running.
marc | wolovim: If that's not the case, I'd love to hear from anybody, or this is also just a,
marc | wolovim: an invitation if anybody believes one of these PRs should get attention sooner rather than later.
marc | wolovim: Daniil, I see you've got quite a few in there. Are any of these… What you would call urgent.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Well, no, I wouldn't say so. I would say, maybe one of the…
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Prs, maybe slightly prioritizes that, to make it possible for, frames to read,
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: key store, to make it compatible with, ERC 8403 and,
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: And, 81.30 to be compatible.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: No, that's only.
marc | wolovim: Okay, sorry, Daniil, I heard only the last few words of that, because I had to switch headphones.
marc | wolovim: Was there any immediate, attention, if you could summarize in 10 seconds for me?
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: No, no, I mean, nothing urgent, yeah, maybe just one, one PR worth, looking into is that PR about, making possible for frames to read, the key store, so, to, to make it compatible, and,
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Let's say, to make it compatible with ERC 8403 and EIP8130.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: So it's kind of, one idea altogether.
marc | wolovim: Okay, if you… if you believe that needs some attention sooner rather than later, I'll suggest
marc | wolovim: That you open a thread for that in the frames?
marc | wolovim: channel and R&D.
marc | wolovim: Does that make sense?
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Yeah, sure. Got it.
marc | wolovim: Okay, thank you.
marc | wolovim: Let's see… I'll assume then the rest of these
marc | wolovim: PRs can wait until after we see how Frame's DevNet Zero goes,
marc | wolovim: Matt, when you get a chance, you can…
marc | wolovim: Chime in, too, to see if you think any of these deserve attention before that is a priority.
marc | wolovim: From here, though, we can move into DevNet updates, and I've asked,
marc | wolovim: EtherX's Yvonne for an update how Etherex testnet is going. He's not able to make the call, but he left a…
marc | wolovim: A note that describes some of their recent activity says the Frame's testnet has been live for 14 days. Three client implementations are validating the network now as Ethrex, Geth, and Nethermind.
marc | wolovim: Almost 400 frame transactions sent from about 21 distinct senders.
marc | wolovim: And… Looks like… s… s…
marc | wolovim: There's some initiatives to… to improve tooling.
marc | wolovim: Okay.
marc | wolovim: Would… would anybody else like to speak to, activity or participation in the Ethrex, testnet? Is there anything we've learned so far that is worth highlighting, or any point… pain points we want to…
marc | wolovim: To, mention specifically.
Justin Florentine: This is Justin from the Besu team. We have not joined yet, and I was wondering what type of criteria we want to use to, you know, make sure that when we do join, we don't break the testnet, i.e.
Justin Florentine: Hive tests, kurtosis configs, anything from ELs, like, what do we got as far as, you know, minimum amount of functionality that we want to test for before we jump on that network?
marc | wolovim: Maybe Daniil could speak to that, if,
marc | wolovim: if nobody else has insight, I know that the EF… Go ahead, Daniel.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Yeah, sure. So, if I remember correctly, it's only the latest version of ELS tests, the requirement, to, to participate in the…
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: DevNet, and yeah, you should contact Yvonne, so he will provide all the required information to you.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: To connect to their, DevNet. And one, tiny note, maybe it's, less relevant, is just, notice that, we have, kind of different, limitation for, verification prefix.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: It's not a consensus issue, it's just, mempool, stuff, so yeah, maybe we, we can, make it, bigger, because, like, current, current default is, 100…
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: K, and, our implementation, is, 300K to, to allow some, let's say, more complex frame transactions to, to be included, into the blocks, so, yeah. But, yeah, they, anyway, they include it, if we want.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: So, yeah, it's not a consensus, it's mempool stuff.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Yeah, that's it.
Justin Florentine: And I assume we want to use the 8141 branch of ELs as, like, this one here.
spencer: Yeah, I think, I think that's correct. There should also be a Frames DevNet0 branch as well.
spencer: But yeah, this is the latest release, so it's, it's been Guru.
spencer: On our side, it's been…
spencer: Working on… on frames. He's… he's out of office until… the 5th of October, so…
spencer: Yeah, I think I'm planning to pick up where he left off, if there's anything. But as far as I know,
spencer: Yeah, the plan is to, yeah, basically have clients pass our latest release, and then,
spencer: Assuming all the clients pass, then… Yeah, launch… launch the DevNet.
Justin Florentine: Thank you.
marc | wolovim: Great.
marc | wolovim: I think that covers Ethrex testnet, which brings us to Frame's DevNet0, the one that we
marc | wolovim: are looking to, use Panda Ops to launch for us.
marc | wolovim: My understanding is that, the primary reason that's not been done already is just that, some folks have been out of office and are returning now, so…
marc | wolovim: I… I do not have a…
marc | wolovim: a date from them yet, looks like, spencer and Matt have relayed
marc | wolovim: similar sentiments already. So that'll be the first thing I do after this call, is check in with them to see when, when we can get that going, and we'll communicate that in the R&D channel.
marc | wolovim: It is… it's my understanding that at least,
marc | wolovim: Geth, Aetherx, and Nethermind are all ready to go there, so that's… that's plenty of… of clients to get started with.
marc | wolovim: Okay, I'm gonna assume there's nothing left to say on Frame's DevNet 0.
marc | wolovim: We've got the remainder of the call, then, to… to chat about anything else we want to cover.
marc | wolovim: We've got a few comments in, in the agenda issue, one of which is,
marc | wolovim: Anders, has offered to make a short presentation about, unified max fee.
marc | wolovim: Would you like the floor next, Anders, if you're… yeah, you're still in the room?
Anders Elowsson: Sure, I can talk about the things that I discussed in my comment on Get Magicians. Maybe I can try to share my screen here, let's see.
marc | wolovim: Yeah, please go for it.
Anders Elowsson: Wait, I'm trying to… Yeah.
Anders Elowsson: So, there you go. Do you have it? Do you see it?
marc | wolovim: Looks good.
Anders Elowsson: Wait, I couldn't… did you… do you have it? Everything good?
marc | wolovim: Yeah, it looks good.
Anders Elowsson: Okay, great. Yeah, so essentially, we want to discuss, you know, the interaction between Frame transactions and a multidimensional fee-market.
Anders Elowsson: Oh, let's see.
Anders Elowsson: Because Frame transactions aim to be this enduring transaction format.
Anders Elowsson: And, we want to do a multidimensional fee-market in the future, and we want to then sync, you know, the research and fee fields so that we have a seamless transition.
Anders Elowsson: And there's also the Frame transactions change how gas is accounted for inside the EVM.
Anders Elowsson: And this is something that the multidimensional fee-market also needs to do, and so we should try to make sure that these two fit together.
Anders Elowsson: And so there are three things I want to discuss. One idea is to have byte limits for state instead of gas limits for the user. The other is to have a unified max fee instead of a separate max fees per resource, and then to have this discussion about how the EVM gas accounting should be designed.
Anders Elowsson: So today, with EIP 8037, we are adding, its own metering to state.
Anders Elowsson: And if we were to go to a multidimensional fee-market, we would turn all of these nos into a yes.
Anders Elowsson: So it would look something like this. There will be 1 meter per resource.
Anders Elowsson: One base fee per resource, and this helps scaling, because developers can set a safe limit per resource. The market can price each one, and every resource can be used up to its own limit.
Anders Elowsson: And one thing that EIP 7999 does is that it says one single max feed that is fungible across resources.
Anders Elowsson: A reason why we would like to do that is that base fees, they can vary independently, and so even though you set it correctly at… when you send a transaction, it would be enough that one base fee of one of the resources would exceed the maximum.
Anders Elowsson: For the transaction to fail, even though the user is willing to pay enough for the transaction to proceed.
Anders Elowsson: And when you set one single max fee, you can allow the transaction to be executed, even because you don't have these separate limits that can preclude inclusion, even though the user is willing to pay.
Anders Elowsson: There's also some, of course, some minor UX and, for example, dev benefits of having one number here for the max fee instead of several.
Anders Elowsson: So, for Frame Transactions, you would turn the max fee per gas and max fee per blob gas into a single max fee at first.
Anders Elowsson: And then, if we add more resources, we would keep the same max fee.
Anders Elowsson: The priority, however, should still be probably per gas, so that you can link tips to actual consumption.
Anders Elowsson: And the second idea is to do,
Anders Elowsson: a state limit in bytes instead of doing it in gas. And this makes it such that we can be safe across repricing.
Anders Elowsson: So…
Anders Elowsson: We can protect users across fork boundaries when the cost per state bike is adjusted. If the limit is denominated in gas, and the cost per state bike rises, then the transaction may suddenly fail.
Anders Elowsson: So, for example.
Anders Elowsson: Besides protecting users, it also means that wallets do not need to look up the cost per state price to express the limit.
Anders Elowsson: It also, of course, is a more compact encoding.
Anders Elowsson: And it is the natural unit of account.
Anders Elowsson: So these are some reasons for using bytes instead of gas for the state limit, and any future limits in natural units.
Anders Elowsson: And,
Anders Elowsson: This can stay very simple. You can use, you can convert such a state-back limits expressed in the transaction to a gas limit immediately upon processing the transaction.
Anders Elowsson: So you could conserve the old processing scheme that you have.
Anders Elowsson: And then finally, the final point here is to… to,
Anders Elowsson: to discuss how to do EVM gas accounting, and we have been trying to sort this out for the multidimensional fee-market, because you price resources separately.
Anders Elowsson: While today the EVM works with a single limit, and we want to preserve legacy call operations and various operations, we then have to make various trade-offs, and there are then different designs that have been under consideration.
Anders Elowsson: One is to have an aggregate EVM gas, so you have an aggregate gas limit for all resources.
Anders Elowsson: But since they are separate fees, that means that any resource that can consume the gas limit, so it must be funded at the highest base fee.
Anders Elowsson: Then, there's another design that, called Sub-fee Accounting.
Anders Elowsson: And here you have, instead, floating gas prices.
Anders Elowsson: And so the user science limits in native units, which are converted at the relative baseway of the block.
Anders Elowsson: To an aggregate gas limit.
Anders Elowsson: And this means that you parry, you don't avoid… you avoid this problem with the funding shake, but then you have these floating gas prices, so the developer needs to query the gas price if it wants to preserve in a sort of a gas way.
Anders Elowsson: Of the design.
Anders Elowsson: And then, the full multidimensional fee-market, where you preserve these separate limits.
Anders Elowsson: for each resource.
Anders Elowsson: And…
Anders Elowsson: The problem then is, if we have this full multidimensional fee-market, we have to consider how to treat all these legacy gas operations, for example, legacy coals, etc.
Anders Elowsson: And of course, you could just send in proportional for each resource based on the limits, but it's not really perfect for what you would like to do, probably.
Anders Elowsson: And so, the idea then is, one idea is to have a universal overflow channel instead.
Anders Elowsson: And so that would be a separate resource in addition to the other resource… resources that you have.
Anders Elowsson: And when you do a call, for example, then the gas perimeter relates to the universal overflow, so you can control how much you preserve after the universal overflow, and how much is sent into the call.
Anders Elowsson: Whereas all the other resources are sent in full.
Anders Elowsson: And if a resource consumes fully its own limit, its own budget, then it starts drawing from the universal overflow.
Anders Elowsson: And after processing the subcall, you then have the universal overflow that was reserved back in it, and can be used then for any future operations within one frame, then, if we're talking about the Frame transactions.
Anders Elowsson: And this universal overflow could be funded according to any of the three different,
Anders Elowsson: the signs that I mentioned in the previous slides, so that means that we have 6 different options that have been under consideration for the gas accounting.
Anders Elowsson: And if we then look at frames, the new thing of the design here is concerning the state gas, which is a frame-level pool.
Anders Elowsson: When nested calls, it draws from it directly, and it's not forwarded or split.
Anders Elowsson: And so, this has some implications, then, for these legacy gas operations.
Anders Elowsson: Both for execution gas and for state gas. So, for example, can a caller reserve capacity for work after a subcall? For execution gas, yes. For state gas, between frames only.
Anders Elowsson: Can a caller cap the work that the caller performed? For execution goes, yes, and for state guts between frames only.
Anders Elowsson: And DAS measure all remaining capacity? It measures execution gas only, and it does not measure state.
Anders Elowsson: And looking at these two different designs, then, there are a few questions that come up that would be interesting to study or discuss further, I guess.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah.
Anders Elowsson: And one is, how much of the reservation problem can separate transaction frames solve? How much are we solving in frames now? And which needs to remain within ordinary calls?
Anders Elowsson: And what are the implications of this frame… frame design on the need for a universal overflow?
Anders Elowsson: And then, holistically, what should a design identity to both frames and multi-dimensional fee-market look like when it comes to the EVM gas accounting?
Anders Elowsson: So that makes it, 3 different,
Anders Elowsson: ideas here that we can discuss further, the byte-limited idea, the unified max fee idea, and how to proceed with the EVM gas accounting.
marc | wolovim: Thank you, Anders.
marc | wolovim: I see… At least 3 good rabbit holes there. You've got a couple
marc | wolovim: comments in the chat, and I think we should try to timebox this, and
marc | wolovim: get in any comments we can now, but redirect the full conversation, to an appropriate place after, so…
marc | wolovim: Speaking for Matt first, because I generally like this, my only fear is that there may be unexpected situations as a result of, this change. Is this too tinfoil hat? And I was asked,
marc | wolovim: Pretty early in the presentation.
marc | wolovim: And then Chris also has a…
marc | wolovim: A comment as well, if you'd like to respond to either of those.
Anders Elowsson: Unexpected situations, yeah, what unexpected situation might it be?
marc | wolovim: Matt is not able to speak, so he might take a minute to get back to you, if you want to respond to Chris.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, it's better to discuss it afterwards than, yeah.
marc | wolovim: Sure.
Anders Elowsson: And what was Chris's question?
Chris - Base: I didn't really have a question, I was just, saying that we are, yeah, interested in max fee. Like, today on L2, we have this L1 data fee, which is, you know, multi-dimensional, but with max fee per gas, it doesn't kind of make sense to fit in there, because it's not a, like, per…
Chris - Base: a fee per gas, so we just, you know, bill it, without the user having any way to kind of specify a max fee. So, like, we are interested in max fee, but ultimately we do want, you know, parity with frames. Like, we don't want to have, like, you know, the 8130 transaction type just being
Chris - Base: Doing it completely its own thing with, like, gas fields and whatnot. So, yeah, we're interested. Yeah, would like to kind of discuss more on that.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, so I guess,
Anders Elowsson: I think that, if I understand your situation correctly, a max fee would be a good way for you to,
Anders Elowsson: Allow the user to limit the, like, you know, the total transaction cost.
Anders Elowsson: But…
Chris - Base: Yeah, yeah, mine's not a question, so yes, what you're saying is correct. It's helpful for us today, because we do have multi-dimensional fee that we actually don't charge… sorry, we don't allow the user to, specify them or not.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, and so it's just that, this L1 cost, is it, there's a floating price on it, but the sort of, if we would say the gas consumption of this, which is probably the data size, is…
Anders Elowsson: Fixed, perhaps?
Chris - Base: Yeah, the L1 data fee is based on, on data size, yep.
Chris - Base: But yeah, we can chat about, you know, the L2 specifics, for that later. I just wanted to voice that.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, so it's good, yeah, so it seems like it could be a benefit to L2s as well.
Justin Florentine: Anders, I have a quick question for you. Do you think that the max fee should be included in VOPS filtering of the mempool?
Justin Florentine: Meaning that as prices for gas fluctuate.
Justin Florentine: to transactions whose max fees are no longer sufficient? Do they get held? Do they get suspended? Do they get kicked out?
Justin Florentine: Any impact on the VOPS rules from this?
Anders Elowsson: I'm not sure that I have actually read the VOPS rules, but the thing is that with the max fee, what you do is that you compensate for drifts in different resources, so it's like a… it's a benefit that would apply here in the meme pool filtering as well.
Anders Elowsson: So… so what happens is that if two… if you have, like, say that you, in the future, have six different resources, and they drift up and down, but… but the total max fee that you may be forced to pay stays the same.
Anders Elowsson: then the transaction can be included in the case and does not need to be filtered out in the new pool. So it's a benefit there, I would say.
Anders Elowsson: Generalist.
Maria Silva: Personally.
Maria Silva: Brilliant. I would also add, so I think the max fee wouldn't require any additional state or execution besides what we have today, right? So you… in the transaction envelope, you should have everything you need, like, you have the limits.
Maria Silva: And you have the… the max fee, so you can infer what would be, like.
Maria Silva: If the transaction can pay the max fee. Like, if the max fee can pay for the base fees or not.
Maria Silva: So, yeah, I don't see why I need any, like, additional state access than what is today.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, that's correct, yeah.
Anders Elowsson: I think.
Anders Elowsson: Based on my understanding of what we're talking about then.
marc | wolovim: I'd like to timebox this one for another, just a couple minutes here, but…
marc | wolovim: Spencer's also asking if you could comment on the main differences between multidimensional on frames transactions and other transactions. How does multidimensional fee change with 8037 in both frames versus other transactions?
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, so the multidimensional fee-market would, in most of the designs that we are considering, I think that we will remove the 8037 reservoir design, but it's not
Anders Elowsson: It's not, perfectly specified.
Anders Elowsson: But it seems like that is what we would like to do. And, like, tying into that question from Spencer, I guess,
Anders Elowsson: The question here is, like,
Anders Elowsson: Do we use frames for trying to cover?
Anders Elowsson: the specific, legacy Paul.
Anders Elowsson: operations that we cannot cover in a poor analysics, less expressive multidimensional fee-market design, such that the other transactions, the regular other existing transaction formats, instead,
Anders Elowsson: Or, sort of, precluded from Being able to execute legacy.
Anders Elowsson: Operations, legacy… legacy contracts, for example.
Anders Elowsson: At the benefit of simplicity.
Anders Elowsson: That's sort of a deeper question on that.
marc | wolovim: Okay, yeah, Maria's saying the reservoir would be needed for the legacy transactions that don't have separate gas limits.
marc | wolovim: Okay.
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, okay, yeah. Yeah, I guess I haven't even…
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, I mean, there's a… yeah.
Anders Elowsson: There's a question of, if this…
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, at some point, we may… Yeah, yeah.
Anders Elowsson: It's… yeah, it seems like a reasonable comment, but I'm not sure, like, at some point.
Anders Elowsson: Because we have to discuss how the EVM does.
Anders Elowsson: the processing, I'll… yeah.
Anders Elowsson: It's not clear to me exactly.
marc | wolovim: Okay. Seems like we still have plenty to talk about here. Is the… The frames,
marc | wolovim: ETH Magician's post the right place to continue this discussion?
marc | wolovim: Do you want to take it to the R&D server?
marc | wolovim: Where can we continue?
Anders Elowsson: Yeah, it's either way for me, but I think that an answer on the magicians and…
Anders Elowsson: And then go from there.
marc | wolovim: Okay, great.
Anders Elowsson: These comments by Maria was relevant there also, too.
Anders Elowsson: Consider.
marc | wolovim: Okay.
marc | wolovim: That looks good. Before I change gears and, give the mic to Mislav.
marc | wolovim: we… we had a comment from jxom, the maintainer of VM, Which is,
marc | wolovim: very related to this conversation, I think.
marc | wolovim: He started implementing, some… an interface and gave some feedback.
marc | wolovim: Saying JSON RPC on Frame transactions feels underspecified on both the EIP and execution API spec. The main friction we're having right now is that tools need a way to estimate gas for frames.
marc | wolovim: via ETH estimate gas, or other support for gas estimation, fill, an ETH fill transaction.
marc | wolovim: and support for Frame transactions in simulation, whether that's via ETH Simulate V1, or,
marc | wolovim: Yvonne had another proposal to introduce, ETH simulate Frame Transaction.
marc | wolovim: So these are… As we talk about
marc | wolovim: Gas accounting, that's very related to how these functions should or will work in the future.
marc | wolovim: Given that we've got a lot still to talk about, I will suggest we…
marc | wolovim: Pick up this, this thread.
marc | wolovim: async as well. But, if anybody would…
marc | wolovim: like to give any preliminary thoughts, I'll invite that now.
marc | wolovim: Okay, in that case, I'm just gonna post a couple of links. Jxom's comment on the agenda is in this first link.
marc | wolovim: And then… Yvonne's, proposal for ETH simulate Frame Transaction is in this second link.
marc | wolovim: And, from there, I can pass the mic over to Mislav, who wanted to chat about,
marc | wolovim: a compatibility effort between 8130 and frames.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Yep, thanks, thanks for the, for the mic. So yeah, everyone, I'll just be very brief with, with this.
Mislav | Ethlabs: So, one of the efforts that EAS took on for the last few weeks, and that we'll be spearheading in the future, is basically building an 8130 implementation on top of frames.
Mislav | Ethlabs: But going beyond that as well, to implement some additional, standards and efforts around developer tooling, like, coincidentally, I also, like, spoke with, jxom on VM support for these additional things.
Mislav | Ethlabs: So let me just share my,
Mislav | Ethlabs: window briefly. Can you see my browser screen?
marc | wolovim: Yep.
Mislav | Ethlabs: So, one of the things, and I… please don't get, think I'm front-running anyone or anything, like, this is still not published, the reason I'm posting it here, and I'll be reaching out to many other people in the coming day or two, is just to give an idea of what's basically being done here. The core…
Mislav | Ethlabs: premise here is that, you know, even though we have this amazing new thing that's coming to Ethereum, we need to make it tangible to relevant stakeholders, not, you know, the…
Mislav | Ethlabs: The core protocol work is one thing, but actually selling it, shipping it, getting, you know, users to interact with it requires a whole separate,
Mislav | Ethlabs: implementation step. Now, the great thing about, ERC… EIP8130 is that it… it…
Mislav | Ethlabs: kicks, like, a lot of the most important, things into itself. Like, it's a very simple way to express a lot of, things that most clients need from smart accounts, from native account abstraction. And the good thing with 8141 is that
Mislav | Ethlabs: all of this is essentially implementable on top of it, with the right mempool policies, and, you know, a few additional EIPs, which seem to have reasonably popular support.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Such as, you know, parallel nounces and stuff of that sort.
Mislav | Ethlabs: But the standard kind of tries to go a bit further, and it says, essentially, you know, we want security, we want a fully audited, formally verified smart contract on top of
Mislav | Ethlabs: well, both 8130 and 8141, that any wallet developer, neobank, fintech app developer can just plug into their own, you know, stack and work with it. And also reusing existing standards, right? We don't want to fully reinvent the wheel.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Some of these standards are good, some of them are already in production, some of them are supported by major players in the industry, such as, you know, MetaMask, or Safe, or others.
Mislav | Ethlabs: We want to create a collaborative effort where, you know, everyone feels that their contribution is valued, and that their functionality will be exposed within this standard.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Some of the key goals we want to integrate for this standard is obviously full compatibility with 8130. The standard has to be built on 8141 for Ethereum mainnet, but then, additionally, we want EIP7906,
Mislav | Ethlabs: to be supported there, 7715, we… so the idea here is
Mislav | Ethlabs: And this goes now to an opinion. You know, there isn't… there isn't really a consensus here. This document has been made by Ethlabs. It's open for discussion, open for critique, open for changing the… switching around. But the idea is to adapt 7715 and 7710
Mislav | Ethlabs: to work with, 8130 sessions system. It should be relatively easy. I've tested the implementation on Solidity, it should work.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Nicely. One additional thing is to see and explore whether 5792 wallet call API can be extended to support expressiveness around all of this.
Mislav | Ethlabs: maybe it can, maybe it can't. If it can, that's great. If it can't, we probably need to build a new wallet call API standard for apps to express their desires to the wallet.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Huge, huge important thing is now that we're gonna be having batches, custom signature scheme, post-transaction assertions, all these, like, things are gonna make transactions look extremely complicated, and clear signing is super important. And I even think, like, clear signing
Mislav | Ethlabs: Combined with 7906 is a game changer for hardware wallets.
Mislav | Ethlabs: where they would be able to statically reason about the outcome of a transaction, and also show it in a user-readable way on the hardware wallet, within an environment where it's much harder to hack, much harder for a, you know, AI-powered adversary to actually influence what the user is signing.
Mislav | Ethlabs: So these are some of the things. Obviously, Ethereum Foundation has a big push towards, privacy.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Luckily for us, the features exposed within 8130 already kind of satisfy most of the needs for privacy. This is put here, basically, as something that, you know, we also want to push for within the interfaces, within the standards.
Mislav | Ethlabs: And then we have a couple of stretch goals. Now, these are very open to discussion. Like, these might just get dropped fully, or they might, you know, gain popular support, or they might get modified. One of them is smart batching, the idea that, you know, once… when you are, like, swapping and then supplying.
Mislav | Ethlabs: sometimes what happens is you have unknown slippages, and you want to, you know, push the output of one step into the input of the next one. The other one is cross-chain transactions, basically where a single signed payload can execute across multiple chains. And then there is, like, the 4337, 77702, other things.
Mislav | Ethlabs: that are relevant here. And one of the outputs of this, of this document and website is going to be
Mislav | Ethlabs: a mock UI demo, which basically shows, to… to people how, like, with a hardware wallet, an app, and a software wallet, like, how an actual
Mislav | Ethlabs: Frame's interaction could look like in the future. Like, this wallet simulates state changes, then encodes a transaction assertion with 7902,
Mislav | Ethlabs: And then when you review it on the wallet, you see clear signed steps in a batch, right? And then you also see clear signed assertion in your hardware wallet, where you can statically reason about what's gonna happen when your security goes through the roof.
Mislav | Ethlabs: And then, additional, of course, every account has multiple keys. How key management works, yeah, basically, everyone's gonna be invited to participate here to, basically, you know, add your own opinion. But yeah, basically, I think we have to work together as an industry to come up with,
Mislav | Ethlabs: with a common standard, you know, that we can all pitch to stakeholders. That's it from my…
marc | wolovim: Super exciting to see all those puzzle pieces put together in one place. Before I invite, broad feedback, where… where is this conversation going to continue? Where do you want people to engage with you?
Mislav | Ethlabs: So, with TBD, I think maybe, well, definitely there's gonna be an Ethereum Magicians post, there's gonna be all the standard channels. This is gonna be converted into an ERC, so there's gonna be the GitHub repo to comment.
Mislav | Ethlabs: I am open towards which specific, like, communication channel is the best, whether it's gonna be Telegram group, a Discord channel, or Signal, or something else. But yeah, like, it's… initially, I think it's just gonna be, like.
Mislav | Ethlabs: published with a Telegram group link, anyone can join, and then, you know, we can move to, like, more formal stuff later down the line, but also open for feedback there.
marc | wolovim: Great, thanks Daniil?
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Yeah, thank you for the presentation. I just wanted to ask, have you considered ERC 8403 as a key management?
Mislav | Ethlabs: So 84… 8403 is something that came, somehow I've… I've, missed the discussion around it. It came up recently, and I… I would definitely want to include it. I think the…
Mislav | Ethlabs: the…
Mislav | Ethlabs: tree structure and pushing the roots is something that would be a good way to do the key store. Beyond that, as far as I remember, there was this conversation with WalletConnect about
Mislav | Ethlabs: potentially having, like, off-chain authority. I'm even thinking on some ways, like, we can…
Mislav | Ethlabs: for all the L2 ecosystems, we could use the canonical bridges for message passing to, like.
Mislav | Ethlabs: configure the same configuration, and there, like, this type of approach might be really good. So, yeah, definitely, we'll be adding.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: All right, thank you. Yeah, just, just wanted to ask you to provide some feedback on the ERC, to check if it works, for you and for all your AORD and your system. Thank you.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Yeah, happy to do so. I think most of the feedback there should come from,
Mislav | Ethlabs: 8130, authors, just because it's, like, the… it modifies the view of the key store, I think, and…
Mislav | Ethlabs: For my efforts, specifically, of coordinating, like, a common interface, it's… whether it's, like, an old-school keystore or this different type of key store doesn't…
Mislav | Ethlabs: doesn't influence me so much. I'll definitely give my personal opinion, but, you know, I think it's more relevant to just synchronize that the key stores are the same everywhere.
marc | wolovim: We've got plenty of time left in the meeting. Are there any… Additional thoughts on this?
marc | wolovim: From a personal perspective, I just want to call out that I appreciate the attention to downstream adoption. That's going to need a lot of
marc | wolovim: I as an effort.
marc | wolovim: To make that a reality.
marc | wolovim: Appreciate we're already thinking about that now.
Mislav | Ethlabs: Yeah, thanks. I think it's, yeah, it's… a year seems like a long time, but it's gonna take at least a year to get it through the gates with the stakeholders.
marc | wolovim: If no further feedback there, that's everything we've got on the agenda. So, we can wrap early and give everybody their 14 minutes back. So last call, any items we want to chat about?
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: Yeah, maybe, maybe a tiny question about, the future of DevNet, if we can, if we can set the, max verified gas not as, 100K as we have right now, but maybe higher for DevNet, as 500K.
Daniil Ankushin | Nethermind: That allows us to test for complex scenarios, or something.
marc | wolovim: Matt says that's fine to me.
marc | wolovim: I guess we'll get confirmation on… on where we… what direction we want to go with that async as well, and when we talk to PandaOps about setting up the testnet.
marc | wolovim: Okay.
marc | wolovim: Last call again. Otherwise, we're gonna wrap up.
marc | wolovim: Alright, I'm gonna call it then.
marc | wolovim: Thank you, everybody, for joining. Appreciate your time and presentations and contributions. We'll see you in two weeks.
marc | wolovim: Take care.
Chris - Base: Excellent.
Pablo Deymo | Lambda: Bye-bye.